Okay, we pick up on
דף ע"ג, Daf Ayin Gimmel, 73, where at the top, two lines
down from the top. דתניא, De-tanya, we taught in the ברייתא, Beraita,
and we are identifying, working to identify a תנא Tanna that says
that even something כל שדרכו למנות, kol she-darko limnot, we had the
רבי מאיר's Rabbi Meir position of things that are normally counted or
exclusively counted, את שדרכו, Et she-darko, כל שדרכו, kol she-darko, debate of
רבי יוחנן וריש לקיש, Rabbi Yochanan Resh Lakish, but things that are
either exclusively or generally counted are not
בטל. batel. חכמים ורבי עקיבא Chachamim and Rabbi Akiva that said only
a very small number, six or seven things. And now we have
a very expansive definition, which is כל דבר שיש בו מניין, kol
davar she-yesh bo minyan, even something that is occasionally counted, can be
counted,
is not בטל, batel, very large category. Okay. דתניא, De-tanya, we taught
in a ברייתא. Braisa. ליטרא קציעות, Litra ketsiot, if you have a
liter of pressed figs שדרסה על פי עיגול she-darsa al pi iggul
that you have now gone ahead and you have, you know, pressed
them down, you've stomped them, pressed them, this is how you make
the figs. And you know, they would make them in these big
rounds, okay? And so you pressed it in this contraption,
you know, in this device that you would use to press the
figs.
And and you now have this round of figs. דרסה
על פי עיגול ואיני יודע באיזה עיגול דרסה, Darsa al pi iggul
ve-eni yode'a be-eizeh iggul darsa, but you don't know now, you know,
these are figs of תרומה, Terumah, that is the key point here,
and you now pressed them in this עיגול, iggul, but you don't
know which עיגול iggul you pressed them in. There are other figs
that were below it. So the top sort of round is yours,
but there could be 20, 50, you know, different of these devices
and you forgot which one you pressed your תרומה Terumah figs in.
Or על פי חבית, al pi chavit, or you pressed it or,
you know, put it into a barrel, and again there's all these
other, you know, rounds in the barrel, like a round of cheese,
this is a round of figs, and and it's at the top
of the barrel, but you don't know which barrel you put it
in. ואיני יודע באיזה חבית דרסה, ve-eni yode'a be-eizeh chavit darsa, but
you don't know which one you you pressed it in. על פי
כוורת, al pi kiveret, כוורת kiveret literally means like a beehive, but
it's a different type of a container, ואיני יודע באיזה כוורת דרסה.
ve-eni yode'a be-eizeh kiveret darsa. Same idea. רבי מאיר אומר, Rabbi Meir
omer, now רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says there's a debate here of
the debate of תנאים Tannaim of later תנאים Tannaim about what the
earlier תנאים Tannaim held. So here's רבי מאיר's Rabbi Meir take on
the debate of רבי אליעזר ורבי יהושע. Rabbi Eliezer and Rabbi Yehoshua.
רבי אליעזר אומר, Rabbi Eliezer omer, רואין את העליונות כאילו הן פרודות
והתחתונות מעלות את העליונות. ro'in et ha-elyonot ke-illu hen perudot ve-ha-tachtonot ma'alot
et ha-elyonot. So רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer is very lenient because תרומה
Terumah nowadays is דרבנן. de-rabbanan. So he says that even though you
know that it is the top layer, and let's say there are
only, I don't know, you know, תרומה's Terumah בטל batel one in
a hundred, and there's only ten barrels or fifty barrels, so that's
not בטל, batel, it's one of the top layers of these fifty
barrels. But comes along רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer say, and he says
that no, you look at it as if the top layer and
the middle sections of the barrel are all mixed together, even though
you know that the problematic one is on the top. And then
you say, each barrel contains, you know, ten of these rounds, there
are ten barrels, one in a hundred, it's בטל, batel, even though
you really know it's a choice of one of ten of the
top layer. Okay, that's a very lenient position. רבי יהושע אומר אם
יש שם מאה פומות יעלו. Rabbi Yehoshua omer im yesh sham me'ah
pumot ya'alu. No, no. It's only the top layer. So if there
are a hundred top layers, a hundred barrels or a hundred, you
know, whatever these various devices and containers are, then it's בטל, batel,
then it's one of the top layers among a hundred and it's
בטל. batel. ואם לאו הפומות אסורים והשוליים מותרים. ve-im lav ha-pumot asurim
ve-ha-shulayim muttarin. Then the top layer, the top round of each barrel
is forbidden, and what's below it is obviously מותר muttar because there's
no question that the תרומה Terumah is only at the top layer.
So you certainly understand that position, that's the straightforward position, and רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer is willing to be more lenient because it is
תרומה Terumah דרבנן. de-rabbanan.
רבי יהודה אומר, Rabbi Yehuda omer, now that's רבי מאיר's Rabbi Meir
version of the debate. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says, here's the debate.
רבי אליעזר אומר אם יש שם ק' פומות יעלו ואם לאו הפומות
אסורים, Rabbi Eliezer omer im yesh sham kof pumot ya'alu ve-im lav
ha-pumot asurim, that רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer is taking a stronger position.
He is taking what in the previous version was רבי יהושע's Rabbi
Yehoshua position. So even the more lenient one here is already starting
one level up. So רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer is saying, no, you
only look at the top layer of the barrels and you need
a hundred barrels, fine. So now what's the stricter position going to
say? רבי יהושע אומר אפילו יש שם שלוש מאות פומות לא יעלו.
Rabbi Yehoshua omer afilu yesh sham shelosh me'ot pumot lo ya'alu. Even
if there were three hundred mouths, three hundred barrels, לא יעלו, lo
ya'alu, it's not בטל. batel. Why not? תרומה's Terumah בטל. batel. one
in a hundred. So let's take a look, but the answer as
we have seen is going to be this point that he is
saying even something that is sometimes counted like these rounds, actually it's
funny, you would think a round of pressed dates they would be
sold by the round, but on the other hand it does sort
of identify it as ליטרא litra as the weight of it. So
this is for some reason in this category of things that are
occasionally counted and he says that is enough to say that it
is not בטל. batel. I guess because also you would sell the
ליטרא, litra, you could sell it by the liter, you could sell
it as part of the whole barrel, there's other ways you could
sell it but sometimes you would sell it by the round itself.
Okay. And therefore since it's occasionally counted it is not בטל batel
and that's even by תרומה trumah which is rabbinic, so certainly he
would say it by our case of the cows and קרבנות korbanot
which is דאורייתא. d'Oraita. But let's just finish now the ברייתא: baraita:
דרס בעיגול ואיני יודע באיזה מקום בעיגול דרסה, daras b'igul v'eini yodeia
b'eizeh makom b'igul darsah, however if it's somewhere in this עיגול, igul,
this contraption, this device for pressing the figs. And you forgot: did
I do the bottom layer, did I do the middle, did I
do it at the top? You don't even remember where in this
thing you did it. Okay.
באיזה מקום בעיגול דרסה או לצפונה או לדרומה, b'eizeh makom b'igul darsah
o litzfonah o lidromah, was it in the north part of it,
the south part of it? So there everything is part of the
ספק. safek. It's not like it's the top layer. You don't know
where it is. So in that case דברי הכל יעלו, divrei hakol
yaalu, everybody agrees you look at all the figs together and it
is בטל. batel. Okay. So we have identified now different positions of
דבר חשוב, davar chashuv, to the degree to which it's either a
small very identifiable number six or seven for רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
and the חכמים Chachamim or it is things that are counted exclusively,
usually, sometimes, a range of
positions
and ironically the גמרא Gemara feels that cows are less חשוב chashuv
than the things that are את שדרקו למנות et she'darko limnot or
the six or seven of רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and the חכמים
Chachamim but it says you can whatever way there's at least one
תנא tanna that would hold that the cows in our משנה mishnah
are important enough to not be בטל batel because certainly they are
sometimes if not exclusively sold by number. So that's the first answer
because they're דבר חשוב davar chashuv they're sold by number, by number.
רב אשי אמר, Rav Ashi amar, now רב אשי Rav Ashi says
a more satisfying answer. אפילו תימא רבנן, afillu teima Rabbanan, even the
רבנן Rabbanan or רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva that don't buy this category
of דרכו למנות, darko limnot, they would still say in our משנה
mishnah it's not בטל. batel. Why? בעלי חיים חשיבי ולא בטלי, ba'alei
chayim chashivei v'lo batli, something that is a live animal is never
בטל, batel, always stands by itself, is never aggregated and therefore there
is no ביטול bittul and that's why there's no ביטול bittul in
the משנה. mishnah. Fine. So now we have established point number one
in the משנה: mishnah: there is no ביטול. bittul.
Now the גמרא Gemara is going to move and say, I get
it that there's no ביטול bittul but remember when I said to
you there are two ways of thinking about how a mixture of
יבש ביבש yavesh b'yavesh works? Does it work that we look at
it sort of like לח בלח, lach b'lach, it's all one big
aggregate and it's defined by the majority, or do we say let's
pick each one individually and ask
ourselves and therefore assess that each one individually came from the majority?
Well that shift is exactly what the גמרא Gemara does right here.
The גמרא Gemara says, I get that as a collection of cows,
it's not בטל. batel. Each one is significant, it doesn't lose its
identity, it's not בטל. batel. But why don't I turn this collection
into a bunch of individual cows which I'm now just going to
try to use statistics to determine what the identity of each cow
is? Not that it's nullified by the collection and the aggregate that
it's a part of, but that its identity is determined going by
statistics, going by רוב. rov. Okay, that is the other way of
thinking of רוב, rov, not nullification but determining status based on the
likelihood, based on the statistics. And here's how we're going to make
that work.
ונמשך, v'nimshach, set two lines from the bottom of ע"ג עמוד א.
Ayin Gimmel Amud Aleph. ונמשך ונקריב אחד מניהו, v'nimshach v'nikrav echad minaihu,
why don't we just take one out of the mixture? So we're
not going to say the whole mixture is muttar, the forbidden one
lost its identity. But just pick one out and then we're going
to pick the next and the next, one by one, pick it
out of the mixture. ונקריב אחד מניהו v'nikrav echad minaihu and we'll
offer that one up on the altar. ונימא, v'neima, we'll say כל
דפריש מרובא פריש, kol d'parish me-rubba parish, anything that separated, separated from
the majority. What if I take one cow out of the hundred?
What do statistics tell me? This is 99 out of 100 likely
that this is the muttar cow. So I'm going to assume it's
muttar. That's אזלינן בתר רוב. azlinan batar rov. That's not רוב rov
of ביטול bittul of nullification, it's רוב rov of determining status based
on statistics. And each one we will take out and assume that
it is from the majority and each one individually we offer up
on the מזבח. mizbeiach. That seems like a great idea. So the
גמרא Gemara says no, הוי ליה קבוע, havei lei kavua, it's not
פריש, parish, it is קבוע, kavua, it is fixed, top of ע"ג
עמוד ב, Ayin Gimmel Amud Bet, דכל קבוע כמחצה על מחצה דמי
d'kol kavua k'mechtza al mechtza dami and each fixed thing, anything fixed
is like it is 50-50. What does that mean? So this is
a sort of strange rabbinic principle, but I think it can be
somewhat understood.
And it classically applies not to a case where you can't identify
but where you can identify. So for example, the classic case
is nine kosher stores and one טרפה traife store selling meat, and
you find a piece of meat in the middle of the street
and you don't know where it came from. So the הלכה halacha
is you go by רוב, rov, you assume it came from the
majority. Clearly there that's no case of ביטול bittul to be obvious,
right? It's one thing, what's its identity? Nine out of ten likely
it came from the kosher stores, you assume it came from a
kosher store, it's permissible. That's called כל דפריש מרובא פריש. kol d'parish
me'rubba parish. Anything that's separated, separated from the majority, you assume it
came from the majority. But let's say you went to the store
and you bought the meat and then you came home and then
you couldn't remember for the life of you which of the stores
you went to. Okay, and so now what you're asking yourself is
not really
what is the status of this meat. The question you're asking yourself
is which store did I go to? And which store did I
go to, well those stores are each קבוע, kavua, it's not one
thing is separated and which did it come from. It's like which
of these were it and each one is in a fixed location
and therefore you have to treat that as 50-50. Now it's a
little strange, it's still nine times out of ten likely you went
to the permissible store, but the idea is since you are there
looking at all of them together and saying which one of these
was it and you know that the איסור issur forbidden store is
among them, you can't
ignore it. You always are seeing the presence of the טרפה traife
store and therefore you have to say maybe it was from the
טרפה traife store. When you have a piece of meat you're not
looking at the stores, you're looking at the piece of meat and
you're saying this is 90% likely it's kosher so therefore it is
kosher. The stores is an abstraction, all right? But when you're looking
at the stores you cannot ignore the טרפה traife store. So what
the גמרא Gemara is saying
is if these cows scattered by themselves and you were just looking
at a cow and you said what's likelihood that this is אסור,
assur, it's one in a hundred, 99 out of 100 it is
מותר mutar and therefore you could offer it up. But when you
go to the mixture where you know there's a forbidden cow and
you take one of them, then you have to always consider the
possibility that you are taking the forbidden one because the forbidden one
is right there in the mixture. That's the principle of כל קבוע
כמחצה על מחצה דמי. kol kavua k'mechtza al mechtza dami. Okay, so
now that's why you can't take one from the mixture. But I
sort of laid a seed for the next question which the גמרא
Gemara asks. אלא Ella says גמרא, Gemara, נכבשינהו דניידי nichbishinhu d'naidi let
us scatter them, let us move them around and let them move.
So you go ahead and throw a rock among in it or
you yell at them and all the cows scatter and then you
go and you take each one separately and when each one is
now wandering off by itself, okay, it is not קבוע, kavua, it's
just here's a cow, what's likelihood it's kosher? 99 in 100. It
can be used as a
קרבן. korban. Then we'll say כל דפריש מרובא פריש. kol d'parish me'rubba
parish. Anything that's separated, separated from the majority. So I get it's
not בטל, batel, it's not nullified. I get you can't take it
when there is a mixture, but why don't you break up the
mixture and just take each one and engage each one individually? So
אמר רבא, amar Rava, so says רבא, Rava, we'll skip the parenthesis,
גזירה שמא יבאו עשרה כהנים
בבת אחת ויקריבו. gezeira shema yavo'u asarah kohanim b'vat achas v'yakrivu. So
he's dealing with a case of ten cows, not a hundred, or
whatever, anyway, let's say
where ten is at least the majority of the number of cows.
And he says we're concerned about the following. עשרה כהנים asarah kohanim
will take each one will take a cow because you say each
one by itself is okay, and then you'll bring it to the
בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash and you'll שחט shacht each
one and then when it comes time to bring it up on
the מזבח mizbeiach you'll have the blood of all ten cows there
at the same time. And you'll know that in that case one
of them is definitely not kosher. So they'll all be there at
the same time and you won't be able to throw the blood
or רש"י Rashi says. He has the scenario, I don't know, that
there were fifteen cows. So the majority likelihood is that you have
the blood of a טריפה *treifah* cow. But then you're no longer
dealing with them individually because then you'll have each כהן kohein *kohen*
took it separately, but then you'll have it in the בית המקדש
Beit HaMikdash, *Beis Hamikdash*, you'll have all of the blood there at
the same time and how can you move forward when you're encountering
the majority of the of the animals? Then the likelihood is that
there is problematic blood here. So that's what רבא Rava *Rava* says.
So, אמר ליה ההוא מרבנן לרבא l'Rava: *amar lei ha-hu me-rabanan le-Rava*,
so one of the רבנן *rabanan* said to רבא Rava *Rava*, אלא
מעתה מגיסת עשרה *ela me-atah megisat asira*? So are you telling me
the basin makes it forbidden? Meaning the basin where the blood is
collected. Meaning when the כהנים *kohanim* took it individually, each one took
it separately. Okay, and with each one you would say to the
כהן kohein *kohen*, you can assume that that's כשר kosher *kosher*. You
could say דחזקינהו *de-chezkinhu*, you could assume that's כשר kosher *kosher*. And
once you've ruled individually that each one is כשר kasher, *kosher*, it
doesn't now when you're looking at all the blood together we don't
reassess it. We've already made a ruling that each one of those
is כשר kasher, *kosher*. Okay, so as long as they were taken
separately, then we don't go ahead and reassess and look at the
statistics again. Their status has already been determined. So the answer then
of the problematic case is obvious. Fine, don't have the together being
with the blood, have the together being with the taking. So the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, אלא מעתה *ela me-atah*, so the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says משום שמא יבואו עשרה כאן בבת אחת ויקחו *mishum shema
yavo'u asarah kan be-vas achas ve-yikchu*. Okay, so not that they'll be
מקריב makriv *makriv* it בבת אחת *be-vas achas*, throw the blood at
the same time, but they will actually every ten כהנים *kohanim* will
come and again let's just imagine that it's a herd of ten
or at least ten is the majority and each one will grab
their cow after we've scattered the herd at the exact same time.
And then when they're grabbing the cow we cannot sort of say
oh you have to you know you can assume your cow is
כשר kosher, *kosher* because somehow we're looking at all ten כהנים *kohanim*
at the same time and we're sort of saying like ooh one
of these is is not כשר kosher. *kosher* so we can't assume
that your cow is כשר kasher, *kosher*. Alright, it's somewhat similar you
know this is a type of thing that happens in other cases
in הלכה halacha *halacha*. There's a case in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
where there's a road and there's you know two roads and one
of them definitely has טומאה *tumah* on it. And and the principle
is ספק טומאה ברשות הרבים טהור *safek tumah be-reshus ha-rabbim tahor*. So
if one person goes on on road A and he says what's
my status you say you're טהור *tahor*. Then the next person goes
on road B and he says what's my status you know you
say you're טהור *tahor* even if though they both can't be טהור
*tahor*. But if they like both come at the same time and
say what's my status then you have to say okay one of
you is טמא *tamei* we don't know which one you're both טמא
*tamei*. So that's the problem here. They might come at the same
time and we'll be confronted at the same time and we won't
then be able to look at each one individually.
So now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like okay how likely is
that scenario. So the גמרא *Gemara* says עשרה כהנים בבת אחת מי
אפשר *asarah kohanim be-vas achas mi efshar* really? I mean maybe to
have them all slaughter it and have the blood at the same
time you know we can that can happen, but you've scattered the
animals and ten כהנים *kohanim* are each grabbing it at the exact
same time each one a different cow and also you wonder like
is it the moment they grab it the moment they ask the
רב Rav, *rav* like how do you determine that? So that's not
a scenario that really we should worry about. אלא אמר רבא Rava.
*ela amar Rava* so now we have a more satisfying answer rather
רבא Rava, *Rava* says משום קבוע *mishum kavua*.
So the problem is because of קבוע *kavua*. Meaning yes if you
were to scatter it and take it individually it would be מותר
*mutar*. But we do not allow you to do that because we
are afraid that if we let you do that you'll just come
to say why should I bother scattering it and you'll come straight
from the mixture itself. Okay, so in principle yes that will work
you're right okay but we don't let you do that because we're
afraid you'll take straight from the mixture itself without scattering it. All
right now we move on to a related point. אמר רבא Rava's
*amar Rava* says רבא Rava, *Rava* השתא דאמרי רבנן לא נקריב *hashta
de-amri rabanan lo nakriv* now that the רבנן *rabanan* say we can't
be מקריב makriv *makriv* in even if we scatter them because you
know you might come ahead and take an individual one or he
might be saying we can't be מקריב makriv *makriv* you know when
they're in the individual mixture that it's not בטל batel, *batel*. תוספות
*Tosafos* makes that point that even the idea that a דבר חשוב
davar chashuv, *davar chashuv* is not בטל batel, *batel* is probably only
דרבנן *derabanan*. So now that the רבנן *rabanan* say that in this
mixture either as the mixture itself or once they get scattered you
know you know the רבנן *rabanan* say that even though דאורייתא de'Oraisa,
*de-oraysa* maybe you could be מקריב makriv *makriv* it they will not
allow us to use it. Once that's true okay לא נקריב *lo
nakriv* אי נקריב לא מרצי *ei nakriv lo martzi*. If you were
to go ahead and ignore what they said and be מקריב makriv,
*makriv* it anyway okay it would not be accepted as a קרבן
korban. *korban*. So basically the רבנן *rabanan* say let's take the focus
on the scattering because that's what we just spoke about the רבנן
*rabanan* say... Why I say don't take it when it's scattered because
we're גזירה gezeira, you'll come to take it from the תערובת. ta'aroves.
And you ignored them, you scattered it, you took one, you brought
it as קרבן. korban. So you should say, okay, you ignored the
rabbis, they made a גזירה, gezeirah, but דאורייתא, it still should be
כשר kasher because you go by רוב rov and that was likely
a כשר kasher קרבן. korban, And רבא Rava says no, since the
rabbis said you're not allowed to do it, that makes it invalid.
Okay, so we'll see exactly the logic of that in, you know,
as we continue. So let's take a look.
איתיביה itvei רב הונא בר
יהודה Rav Huna bar Yehuda לרבא: חטאת שנתערבה בעולה ועולה שנתערבה בחטאת
אפילו אחת בריבוא ימותו כולם. Chatas shenisarva b'olah v'olah shenisarva b'chatas afilu
achas b'ribbu yamus u'kulam. So we're back to קינים, Kinnim, remember we
had a whole difficult thing about that a few days ago, with
birds. So you got one bird חטאת Chatas mixed up with one
עולה, Olah, okay, or or vice versa, I mean they're mixed up,
even one in a hundred, again they're not בטל, batel. you know,
they're בעלי חיים, ba'alei chayim, they're דבר חשוב, they're not בטל, batel,
so they all have to die. Why? Because you can't go ahead
and bring them all as עולות, olos, you'll be offering one thing
in the wrong place, or you can't bring them all as חטאת,
chatas, you'll be offering at least one of them in the wrong
place. So you have to let them all die. Okay, that's starting
again similar principle, it's not בטל. batel
Now, במה דברים אמורים, b'meh devarim amurim, when is it true? בכהן
נמלך, b'kohein nimlach, if the כהן asks us what should I do?
So we'll say you're not allowed to be מקריב makriv it, one
thing you're going to be מקריב makriv, in the wrong place. אבל
בכהן שאינו נמלך, Aval b'kohein she'eino nimlach, but if the כהן doesn't
ask our advice, and he just goes ahead and he takes the
bird and he does what he thinks he should do, so עשאה
למעלה, aso l'ma'ala, so if he did all the birds above, let's
just talk about two birds, one חטאת chatas one עולה. olah. He
did the two above, which is where the עולה olah is done.
So מחצה כשר מחצה פסול, mechtza kasher mechtza pasul, the one of
them is כשר, kasher. one is פסול, pasul, because the עולה olah
is כשר, you don't know which is which, but you definitely were
legitimately מקריב makriv. the עולה, olah, okay, because you did both of
them above.
למטה, L'mata, if he did both of them below, similar מחצה כשר
מחצה פסול. mechtza kasher mechtza pasul. The חטאת chatas was כשר, the
עולה olah was invalid, you don't know which is which, but you
know you were legitimately מקריב makriv the חטאת. chatas. אחת למטה ואחת
למעלה, Achas l'mata v'achas l'ma'ala, if he did one above and one
below, you could imagine somebody trying to do that, like you accidentally
turned on the lights on שבת Shabbos and you say oops and
you turn them off. So here you got the עולה olah and
the חטאת chatas mixed up, so you feel the way you'll solve
it is you'll bring one above and one below. So the הלכה
halacha is in that case, שניהם פסולים, sheneihem psulim, that you have
to assume that neither was good. שאני אומר, She'ani omer, because I
would say, חטאת קרבה למעלה, chatas kerva l'ma'ala, that you got them
reversed, you brought the חטאת chatas above, ועולה קרבה למטה v'olah kerva
l'mata and the עולה olah below. Okay, so anyway, so why is
that a סתירה stira to what רבא Rava said? Because here it's
exactly that case. We say you're not allowed to be מקריב, okay,
because it's not בטל, batel, but if you go ahead and you're
not allowed to be מקריב the thing in the wrong place, but
if you go ahead and ignore us, then we say we go
by objectively the fact that some of those animals were כשר. So
the fact that we said not to do it does not make
it invalid. So that's a direct contradiction to you רבא. Rava So
the גמרא says, אלא הא כמאן דאמר בעלי חיים נדחין והא כמאן
דאמר בעלי חיים אינם נדחין. ellah ha keman d'amar ba'alei chayim nidchin
ha keman d'amar ba'alei chayim einam nidchin.
So this is like the one that says that בעלי חיים ba'alei
chayim are נדחין, nidchin, and this is like the one that says
that בעלי חיים ba'alei chayim are not נדחין. nidchin. What does that
mean? That means that when an animal is for a certain period
of time as a קרבן, already been sanctified, not able to be
brought, that's called it's נדחה, nidcha, it's pushed away. And then when
it becomes able to be brought, that's נדחה ונראה, nidcha v'neera, it
was pushed away and now becomes fit. And the question is, does
the fact that it was temporarily not able to be brought mean
that it remains disqualified?
And the question is, maybe we would say that by inanimate objects,
like if the blood for a while couldn't be brought and then
it became fit, that it just sticks with the label of of,
you know, invalid, but the there's a debate by בעלי חיים, ba'alei
chayim, live animal, something live is seen I think as more dynamic,
so therefore, you know, even if it got pushed away, you know,
things can change and it that label maybe doesn't stick. That's a
debate. So the גמרא says, well that's the debate that is going
on here. What does that mean? Because for רבא, what רבא point
was is when the rabbis said you are not allowed to scatter
it and to and to take one, that means because of the
rabbinic ruling, okay, these animals, you know, are all cannot be used,
they're נדחה. nidcha. Now, you know, you might already actually say, and
רש"י Rashi sort of discusses this, even without the rabbinic ruling they're
נדחה, nidcha, because until you scatter it, it also can't be used,
they're now part of the mixture and they can't be used until
you scatter it.
So now the reason it remains invalid is because you say בעלי
חיים נדחין. Ba'alei Chayim Nidchin. Once it was off the table, it
remains off the table. Even if now you went ahead and you
scattered it and took it and made it that you could go
by רוב. rov. Okay, the one that says that by the birds
if you brought them all above, you know, one of them counted,
says it's true, the rabbi said don't do it, and that took
it off the table, but now you did it and the הלכה
halacha is that בעלי חיים ba'alei chayim are not נדחין, nidchin, and
even though you shouldn't have done it, when now ahead it was
done and the reality is that it really is fit and therefore
it remains okay. Okay, so that's the debate. So now the גמרא
says הרי שחוטין harei shechutin
one minute,
that's questionable if that's going to answer because there's a case of
when it comes to something that's already been שחט shachted דכולי עלמא
נדחה, dekuli alma nidche,
everybody says that once something is שחט shachted and it becomes unusable,
it can't be used again. And I'm going to show you that
in an analogous case that it can't be used because the rabbis
made a restriction, if you went ahead and did it it will
still be good. Okay, and then according to you logically it should
be נדחה, nidche, it should have been pushed off and remained pushed
off. ותנן u'tnan we taught in the משנה Mishnah top of 74
עמוד א׳, amud aleph, רבי אליעזר אומר Rabbi Eliezer omer אם קרב
הראש של אחד מהן יקרבו כל הראשים. im kerev harosh shel echad
meihen yikrevu kol haroshim.
So if, you know, basically you didn't, you got the heads of
עולות olot
mixed up, you know, and one of them was a בעל מום,
baal mum, so one of these קרבנות korbanot you can't put on
the מזבח, mizbe'ach, these heads, but you don't know which one, it's
mixed up in the heads of a lot of other sheep that
you should put up on the מזבח. mizbe'ach. And so and רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says so the הלכה is you're not allowed to
do it, same idea. Don't do it if there's a פסול pasul
one. The rabbis are telling you not to do it. And then
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says if you went ahead and ignored us,
אם קרב הראש אחד של אחד מהם im kerev harosh echad shel
echad meihem and you put one of them up, then now we're
going to actually now let you even do all the rest, יקרבו
כל הראשים. yikrevu kol haroshim. Now you can assume, you shouldn't have
done it, we told you not to, but now that it was
done, we can assume, oh, we'll assume that the bad one was
the one that was already brought up and we'll let you bring
up all the rest. Now, why do we assume that? Most likely
the bad one is still in the mixture. But that is just
again an evidence that some of this aspects of things not being
בטל because there's significance might only be a rabbinic ruling, so we'll
be lenient if you already, according at least according to רבי אליעזר,
Rabbi Eliezer, since it's only rabbinically that it's not בטל, that if
you put one of them up we'll assume that it was the
problematic one and now you can put up the rest. But what's
relevant for us is, at least initially you weren't supposed to put
any of them up. So they were נדחה, nidche, they were off-limits,
not able to be brought up. And then you went ahead and
you ignored us and now you can go ahead and put them
up, and they're כשר, and they don't lose their status. So according
to you רבא, right, that if you רבא say once you hold
of the principle of נדחה nidche then it remains no good, then
everybody holds of נדחה nidche by something that's שחט, shachted, so why
doesn't that, why does רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer say it can work?
So the גמרא says הוא דאמר כחנן המצרי. hu de'amar k'Chanan HaMitzri.
He says like חנן המצרי Chanan HaMitzri because חנן המצרי Chanan HaMitzri
says even something that is שחט shachted there's no principle of נדחה.
nidche. דתניא detanya we taught in a ברייתא, braita, חנן המצרי אומר
אפילו דם בכוס מביא חברו ומזווג לו. Chanan HaMitzri omer afilu dam
bekos meivi chaveiro u'mezaveig lo. Okay, that this is talking about the
שעיר המשתלח sa'ir hamishtale'ach and the שעיר sa'ir that's brought, you know,
inside the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, and that even if, you know,
if the שעיר המשתלח sa'ir hamishtale'ach died and the other you have
the blood of the שעיר sa'ir that's supposed to be brought and
sprinkled inside the בית המקדש, he says you don't have to go
back and pick now two goats and do it again, you actually
can just bring a live goat and that can be the שעיר
המשתלח sa'ir hamishtale'ach and that can be the partner for this blood
that's from the שעיר sa'ir that was already slaughtered. And even though
in the interim now when you have the dead שעיר המשתלח sa'ir
hamishtale'ach this blood can't be used because it doesn't have the partnering
שעיר, sa'ir, so that's clearly נדחה nidche by blood, and nevertheless חנן
המצרי Chanan HaMitzri says I don't hold of נדחה nidche even by
blood, even by something שחט. shachted. It's true the blood could not
be used for that time, but now that you brought the other
שעיר sa'ir it can be used and go forward. So basically what
רבא is saying is once the rabbis tell you you're not allowed
to be מקריב, okay, even if it's a גזירה, even if for
whatever reason, you know, or they just don't want you to bring
the אסור assur thing, even though the כשר things can still be
brought, they don't want to, they don't want to allow that at
the expense of bringing the non-כשר thing, because one of those things
is not כשר. So therefore רבא says that makes everything נדחה. nidche.
Pushed off, off the table, you're not allowed to be מקריב. And
if you go ahead and choose to be מקריב it anyway and
now or scatter it, and now you can assume it comes from
the majority, it doesn't matter. Once it's pushed off, even if it's
only because of this rabbinic ruling, it remains נדחה nidcheh and you
cannot reuse it. And any position that says you can reuse it,
not reuse it, excuse me, and it remains no good even if
you went ahead and offered it. And any position that says that
it is good if you went ahead and offered it is a
position that does not hold of the principle of נדחה. nidcheh. And
therefore, once you didn't listen to us and now it becomes fit,
now it actually does work. It's like somebody I know that says
I would much rather ask for, my principle is, ask for forgiveness,
not for permission. So in this case, that would actually work, but
you're not supposed to do it. For רב, it would not work,
it would remain נדחה. nidcheh. Okay, we will end here.